A Guide to the Board of Public Works - James River Company Records, 1794-1840
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
A Guide to the Board of Public Works - James River Company Records, 1794-1840
The Library of Virginia
BPW 83, 30030
6.5 cu. ft. and 2 volumes (19 boxes)
Virginia Board of Public Works
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
No acquisition information available.
Biographical Information
The company was chartered by an act of the General Assembly of January 14, 1785. The purpose of the company was to extend the navigation of the James River to its "highest practicable point." By an act of February 17, 1820 the James River and Kanawha Company was chartered as successor to the James River Company; the state of Virginia subscribing to 3/5 of the stock. With the expansion of the railroads at the end of the Civil War the company fell on hard times. On March 5, 1880 the company was sold to the Richmond and Alleghany Railway Company.
Scope and Content
Records, 1794-1840, including accounts, agreements, contracts, correspondence, deed books, field notes, financial statements, lists of stockholders, journals, maps, minute books, plans, receipts, reports, sketch books, vouchers, and warrants of the James River Company. Included are records concerning the Blue Ridge Canal, the Kanawha Road and river improvements, and the work on the James River itself.
Contents List
- Deed Book 1, 1821-1871. (Box 186)
- Minute Book D, 1835-1847. (Box 187)
- Receipts and Warrants, 1828-1831. (Box 187)
- Journal B, 1832-1840. (Box 188)
- List of subscribers, 1832-1835. (Box 188)
- Plan of Guard Lock for Tuckahoe Creek (with maps see: 755.42 Z1), 1822. (Box 189, Folder 1)
- Field Notes, New River, 1 volume, 1819. (Box 189, Folder 2)
- Field Notes, Craigs Creek, 1 volume, 1819. (Box 189, Folder 3)
- Field Notes, James, Greenbrier, and New Rivers, 1 volume, 1819. (Box 189, Folder 4)
- Field Notes, 3 volumes, 1819. (Box 189, Folder 5)
- Field Notes, 3 volumes, 1818. (Box 189, Folder 6)
- Field Notes, Various surveys by Hugh P. Taylor, 1 volume, 1819. (Box 190, Folder 1)
- Field Notes, Irish Falls to Lynchburg (labeled 3rd sketch book to accompany the 4th field book), 1 volume, 1824. (Box 190, Folder 2)
- Field Notes, James River to Purgatory Mountain, 1 volume, 1824. (Box 190, Folder 3)
- Field Notes, Purgatory Mountain to Covington (labeled experimental survey no. 7 and no. 8), 2 volumes, 1824. (Box 190, Folder 4)
- Field Notes, Wood's Island to Dunlap's Creek (labeled 5th sketch book to accompany the field books nos. 7-8), 1 volume, 1824. (Box 190, Folder 5)
- Field Notes, Scott's Mill-race to Tye River, 1 volume, 1824. (Box 190, Folder 6)
- Field Notes, Blue Ridge Gap, 1 volume, 1824. (Box 190, Folder 7)
- Field Notes (labeled: from Mother's Dam to Manchester; sketch book No. 1 to acompany field books no. 1 and 2; 1st appendix to field books; 2nd appendix to field books; 4th sketch book from the North Branch to Wood's Island to accompany 6th and 7th field books; survey from Beaverdam Creek to Maiden's Adventure), 6 volumes, 1824-1825. (Box 190, Folder 8)
- Field Notes (labeled: 1st field book of the survey of James River from Maiden's Adventure to the Blue Ridge; 2nd field book of the survey of James River from the Blue Ridge to Covington; 3rd field book of the survey of James River to accompany the 1st field book; 4th field book of the survey of James River to accompany the 1st field book; 5th field book of the survey of James River to accompany the end of the 1st and beginning of the 2nd field book; 6th field book of the survey of James River to accompany the 2nd field book; Dam and Canal near Mayo's Bridge), 7 volumes 1827-1829. (Box 191, Folder 1)
- Field Notes, Kanawha Turnkpike Extension (labeled: 1st book to Kelly's X Witcher's creek; 2nd book from Witcher's creek to Campbell's creek; 3rd book from Campbell's creek to Charleston and changes made above Kelly's creek; 4th book from Big Sandy to Barboursville; 5th book from Barboursville to station 614 near Ellis on the Hurricane; 6th book from station 614 near Ellis' on the Hurricane to Charleston), 6 volumes 1829. (Box 191, Folder 2)
- Field notes, Kanawha Turnpike Extension (labeled: from its present termination to Charleston; continuation of the survey of a route by Sackett's Creek), 2 volumes, 1829. (Box 191, Folder 3)
- Map (Lexington Turnpike, Jacksons River, Dunlaps Creek, Kanawha Turnpike, Plan of Covington), undated. (Box 192, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, reports, financial statements, and certificates of stock, 1794-1822. (Box 192, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, reports, financial statements, and certificates of stock, 1823-1824. (Box 192, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, reports, and financial statements, 1825-1827. (Box 192, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, reports, and financial statements, 1828-1831. (Box 192, Folder 5)
- Correspondence, reports, financial statements, and list of stockholders, 1832-1835. (Box 192, Folder 6)
- Lower Canal contracts, 1820-1823. (Box 193, Folder 1)
- Lower Canal receipts, John Staples, Superintendent, part 1, 1823. (Box 193, Folder 2)
- Lower Canal receipts, John Staples, Superintendent, part 2, 1823. (Box 193, Folder 3)
- Accounts of labor on canal, includes names of labourers, 1823. (Box 193, Folder 4)
- Lower Canal, Fencing and bridges, letters and papers, 1823-1825. (Box 193, Folder 5)
- Lower Canal, Proposals and agreements for work, 1826-1835. (Box 193, Folder 6)
- Kanawha River Improvement, John Bosher, Superintendent, Letters, accounts, contracts, etc., 1821-1822. (Box 194, Folder 1)
- Receipts for surveys, 1821-1824. (Box 194, Folder 2)
- Kanawha Road, Correspondence, contracts, etc. with John Caruthers for construction, 1821-1825. (Box 194, Folder 3)
- Kanawha Road, James Moore, Contractor for Greenbrier and Gauley Bridges, Contracts, etc., 1823-1826. (Box 194, Folder 4)
- Kanawha River improvement, Contracts, correspondence, etc., 1823-1832. (Box 194, Folder 5)
- Blue Ridge Canal, Correspondence (includes 2 letters between James Brown, Jr., Second Auditor, and John Robertson, Attorney General), 1824. (Box 194, Folder 6)
- Blue Ridge Canal, Land papers, condemnations, etc., 1825-1832. (Box 194, Folder 7)
- Blue Ridge Canal Turnpike, Correspondence, etc., 1831-1836. (Box 194, Folder 8)
- ,. (Box 195, Folder 1)
- ,. (Box 195, Folder 2)
- ,. (Box 195, Folder 3)
- ,. (Box 195, Folder 4)
- ,. (Box 195, Folder 5)
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.
- ,.